welcome you are about to view a recorded
talk of the mathematical consciousness
science online seminar series held in
2020 this seminar series aims to explore
the role of mathematics than the
scientific study of consciousness and
hopes to connect researchers who have an
interest in this topic while every
session of the seminar consists of a
talk and discussions the latter are not
recorded and the following will only
contain the talk we hope you will enjoy
it for further information please visit
our website seminar math - consciousness
org I'm going to go through the basic
idea from or approach the basic ideas
from a couple of perspectives just to
put everything into context I want to in
particular end up at this notion of a
dual aspect information geometry and how
that emerges and how it inherits from
predictive processing or constructivist
views of the brain and the second agenda
is just to start to fine-grain or drill
down on different kinds of inference
that may map to different aspects of
sentience and consciousness so that's
where I'm trying to go let me start by a
nod to where much where much of these
ideas come from so I came into this
really from the point of view of
predictive coding and predictive
processing as it's now currently known
the idea of being here that we actively
construct explanations for our sensorial
so this is nicely illustrated by this
oil painter in the 16th century famed
for doing still lives that when viewed
from another perspective have a very
different interpretation
so if before you saw a bowl of
vegetables and now you see a face the
point be made or the point that he was
making is that this face this
this hypothesis this fantasy for what
cause these sensory impressions is
coming from the inside out
so this turns on its head the 20th
century view of information processing
where the information comes from the
outside-in impresses itself on to use
Helmholtz's was a nervous mechanism and
somehow information is extracted to
conclude there is a face and more looks
at it from from an active or
constructive point of view where you're
checking or using the sensory
information to check revise update your
beliefs that you already have in mind
about what could have caused those
sensory inputs and indeed this is the
exactly the view championed by Helmholtz
objects are always imagined as being
present in the field of vision as would
have to be there in order to produce the
same impression on the nervous mechanism
that idea I think has had quiet traction
since its introduction for example the
ideas of Richard Gregory are about
perception as iPods is testing the
notion formerly has been taken up to
great effect by people in machine
learning like Geoffrey Hinton and Peter
Dayan borrowing ideas from Richard
Feynman specifically variational
free-energy formulations and quantum
electrodynamics and making that work or
unpacking that in the context of the
Bayesian brain or more generally an
inference gloss on this ability to
confirm your hypotheses about what
caused your sensory data at this point
in time so just taking that notion of
sensory impressions what we have a hand
is is the challenge of understanding how
you and I make sense of the shadows on
our sensory epithelia so what are
causing those shadows that we are
witness to impinging upon our
eyes ears and indeed our interceptors
the solution to that problem that
inference problem you can just lift from
standard Bayesian statistics or machine
learning in the latter days and one ends
up with a relatively simple scheme which
can be construed in terms of something
called Bayesian filtering in the
neurosciences it's now become known as
predictive coding but it is the same
thing at all it's saying is that if I
want to optimize my expectations the the
belief I have about the causes of some
sensory impression let's say that this
was our sensory input and all I have to
do is to minimize a quantity that we can
write out as essentially a precision
weighted prediction error so this
equation here is a differential equation
that dot means rate of change this means
that this is an equation of motion or a
flow so flow or like on a functional or
free energy potential here there is a
function of the expectation and the
sensory impressions here and this is a
form of a Kalman filter or predictive
coding scheme so this is the prediction
and these are the particular weighted
prediction errors so what are the
prediction the prediction errors well
let's say we had this sensory input and
we have this expectation about what
could have caused this sensory
impression here and the idea is that we
can generate through a journey of model
what we would have seen if this was
correct and this provides a prediction
that is subtracted from the sensation to
form a prediction error such that if you
were able to minimize the prediction
error so that these two things were the
saying you have effectively found an
explanation or a hypothesis that is a
sufficient explanation to explain your
sensorial so the crucial point here
that it is a sufficient explanation it's
not necessarily the very little
expression you will never know what's
out there but if you can get through
life minimizing your prediction errors
then you've got a sufficiently good
model to navigate and survive so that
perspective provides a nice formal
intuitive way of understanding
perception it also enables you to
accommodate action in the in this
service of minimizing prediction error
because if the imperative is say to
minimize prediction error which will
later become this free energy functional
then there are two ways we can do that
so if prediction errors sensations -
predictions we can either change the
predictions in our head to make them
more like the sensations or we can
change the sensations by acting upon the
world to resample to palpate it in a
different way to make the sensations
more like the predictions so both action
and perception by our changing
sensations and predictions are just
playing the same game and in hand trying
to minimize that prediction error so we
now have if like as an intuitive picture
of active inference inference under
action where you are in charge of
harvesting those data that you predict
so in some sense your actions now become
self-fulfilling prophecies and we'll see
an example of that later so that's the
the other sort of the kind of
introduction to these ideas I might give
a psychology audience or a psychophysics
audience and you're a biological
audience what I want to do now is to
change the tempo of the talk and just
put that to one side and see if we can
get to the same conclusions and the same
kind of mathematical phenomenology from
a purely first principle statistical
approach and if we can what implications
does that have for sentience
so the way I'm going to do that is
quickly go through a treatment of the
statistics of light of self-organization
with a special emphasis on Markov
blankets and I've written a conic
systems here and should really be
non-equilibrium steady-state the
implications of those non equilibrium
steady states with Markov blankets in
terms of information geometry and ago
illustrate that with a numerical
simulation of some active matter or a
primordial soup and I'm going to close
with different grades of sentience and
active inference that I'm hoping will
speak to different kinds of
consciousness or the saw that you will
be more familiar talking about so let's
start with this question post by
scrolling up how come the events in
space and time which take place within
the spatial boundary of a living
organism be accounted for by physics and
chemistry so we're not going to address
that question head-on although we will
implicitly answer it what we're going to
do first of all is just focus on this
notion of a spatial boundary and he
would be the first person to a knowledge
that boundary is itself a statistical
object a construct and for those people
who don't know what a Markov blanket is
I'll just quickly take you through it
imagine you've got some universe and
these nodes of this graph here are
states of some universe some systemic
States and they are influencing each
other or they have statistical or
probablistic dependences denoted by the
arrows here if I dis identify some set
of states here McCullough's internal
States then the Markov blanket comprises
the parents the children and the parents
and the children of these internal
states and its role or its importance is
that it provides a statistical shield or
set of states that mean that if I wanted
to predict what's going to happen to me
my internal States now given the entire
rest of the universe
I will only ever need to know
these blanket states that enshroud me
here so all the information out there
pertinent to what's going on in here is
contained within the blanket states so
technically these states are independent
of these states given or conditioned
upon the state of the blanket states now
I'm going to make a further move which
will make a lot more sense in the next
slide and it's going to introduce a
bipartition of the blanket States into
active states that influence external
states but do not influence internal
states and sensory states that influence
internal states that are not influenced
by the internal states and you may be
asking why have I done that well if one
just looks at this probabilistic
structure this very elemental statement
of a dynamical world that somehow is
coupled through dependencies and causal
structures then we can look at these
blanket States and in particular the
partition into sensory active states in
conjunction with the internal states
that they encompass as the states of a
particle and by a particle I mean
something that could be as big as a
grain or as small as an electron or
something of the size of a cell all of
these things particular things have in
common a Markov blanket and in one sense
they have two because if you didn't have
this conditional independence you would
not be able to measure in a statistical
sense the difference between the thing
or the particle and anything else it
would become systole part of the
universe so I'm just sketching out why
that or how that unpacks for example in
the brain we can consider all the
internal brain States or the synaptic
activity efficacy connectivity of inside
the brain as the internal brain states
and they influence active states or
autonomous
nervous system our our motor effectors
that cause changes in the external
states that then impinge back on the
sensory states that in turn influence
the internal states and the missing
dependencies really here and here define
this Markov blanket so there's an
exchange between the internal and the
outside but it has to be mediated with
this certain with this bi-directional
impermeable interface that is the Markov
blanket where the sensory states mediate
the inference of outside on the inside
and the active States conversely the
inside on the outside and exactly the
same structure holds for a little cell
where the surface states could
constitute Li and the cell receptors
could constitute the sensory states
affecting the internal millia of the
cell in terms of its intracellular
processing and chemicals active States
could be actin filaments that support
the sensory states that can endow the
cell with a motility that change the
external Millia
that again reports back in influences
and sensory states so what we have here
that inherits just from having a Markov
blanket which every particle or thing
must have is a circular causality that's
very reminiscent of the action
perception cycle I use the word sector
causality deliberately because that's
going to come back and do some heavy
lifting later on right so what I want to
do now is just put a bit of statistical
physics on the Markov blanket but to do
so I'm just I'm going to have to dis
back off a little bit and ask you to
forget about the Markov blanket for a
moment and just bear with me why we why
we well we drill down on
self-organization in any arbitrary
system then we're going to see what
happens when we put the Markov blanket
back in play again so what I've done
here is just produce a little graphic of
some universe or some system here just
depicted in terms of two states one
state here one state here so to any one
point in time the state of the universe
is a point and as time goes on it moves
around in the state space tracing at a
manifold or an attracting set that in
fact is called methodically attracting
set or a random dynamical attractor or a
pull back attractor now the kinds of
particles that were going to be talking
about all systems are those that endure
over time and in that instance that
licensed me to understand the density of
these trajectories as they unfold over
time say for example I was getting up in
the morning having my coffee going out
to work well that's what I used to do
before career for her Elizabeth but then
you know following the my my normal
trajectory over the day of course this
could actually represent my heartbeat or
it could be on a time scale over years
we have Christmas and Eastern or some
holidays irrespective of the time scale
the nature of these states this kind of
object must be in play and it means that
I can interpret the density of these
trajectories in terms of the probability
that if you've sampled me at any one
point in my heartbeat or any time during
the day or during the year this also
denotes a probability you'll find me in
that state and I'm going to refer to
that as a non-equilibrium steady state
density now the important move that I
can make just by stating or stipulative
fining the kinds of systems we that
we're interested in as dynamical systems
that have this that these dynamics that
conform to a long-run form and the
Endura of a time means I can derive from
this certain implications which actually
take us back to that predictive coding
scheme that we took we started off with
so I won't go through this in detail but
just to reassure you them there exists a
simple mathematical description of the
the way in which this non-equilibrium
steady state density evolves over time
as a function of the amplitude of random
fluctuations on the flow F of the states
as a function of where they are in state
space and the peak corresponding to the
this non-equilibrium steady state
density here so this is a Fokker Planck
equation you may know it as the master
equation you may notice a scroller
equation these are all equivalent
formulations of this basic density
dynamics ensemble dynamics for us we can
do something quite useful here because
we just said that these this object this
probability density does not in and of
itself change over time so we can set
this to zero and we can look at the
solution to this Fokker Planck equation
and when we do so we see something very
interesting what we see is that we can
express the flow of states at any point
in state space here as effectively a
mixture of a gradient descent or in this
integrated ascent on the log of this
probability or over state space so this
inherits from something called the
Helmholtz decomposition this amplitude
of the random fluctuations determines
the degree to which I'm hill climbing
this Q here denotes circuitous or Suren
oil flow around probability gradients
I'm gonna unpack that for you in the
next slide but the key point to take on
this is if things exist in particular
those things with Markov blankets
because to have a thing you have to have
a Markov blanket then we can write down
this kind of equation and this kind of
equation essentially means you are doing
a gradient flow or gradient ascent or
descent on some quantity that has
related the probability of me being in a
particular state so for those people not
familiar with the fokker-planck equation
I just want to illustrate that imagine
that I have a piece of ink and I'm
dropping it into some solvents a glass
of water and what I would expect to
happen normally is that the ink
molecules would dissipate due to the
random fluctuations and distribute
themselves over the entire volume of the
solvent that's not the kind of system
that we're interested in here though
because we just said these systems
gather themselves up together and are
restricted to their attracting settler
pull back attractor so this is what this
kind of system would look like is it
would look as if it was in down with
some capacity to do inverse diffusion to
actually diffuse up concentration
gradients and that's exactly what this
equation says what it's saying is that
the flow in order for this attracting
set to be realized to attain this
non-equilibrium steady state has to have
two components one it has to climb the
gradients of the probability well
strictly speaking the log probability of
the kinds of states it is find found in
and this Q term here is this circular
flow solenoid flow around the I so
probably
contours basic structure the way to
predicate the arguments on what I want
to do with this slide is just convince
you or at least provide some some
graphical evidence that formalism that
we've just briefly rehearsed underwrite
nearly all of physics as we know it so
special cases of this you will have done
at school so when they amplitude of
those random fluctuations on the flare
goes to zero we arrive at conservative
systems of the sort that would be useful
for describing massive bodies
gravitation Newtonian laws Lagrangian
mechanics where it's all about this
circular flow hence the planets
revolving around the Sun and the moon
around the earth we can look at the
other special case where we eliminate
the solenoidal flow or at least increase
the amplitude of random fluctuations and
then what we have is a mechanics that
applies to fluctuating systems basically
fluctuation dissipation theorem and all
of statistical mechanics and statistical
thermodynamics with the usual constants
and proportionality here Boltzmann's
constant and all the things you don't
know about entropy and enthalpy again at
school we can make another move we can
just say somewhat arbitrarily although
there are good reasons for doing it we
can just express that non-equilibrium
steady state density as the product of
two complex roots and if we do that and
following through we get quantum physics
and this is actually just a restatement
of that fokker-planck equation that we
saw earlier on however if you remember
the reason we're doing this is to see
what are the implications of having a
Markov blanket and this is where it
starts to get more interesting from our
perspective so there's another kind of
physics out there there is unique to
systems that have this by partition into
internal and external
separated by the blankets fades and
that's as phasing mechanics which we've
mentioned in terms of this perception
action cycle so remember before that
everything has to be described as this
this solenoidal gradient flow on the
negative on the logarithm of the the non
equilibrium steady state density that
has to be true for the internal states
and the active States name in the
blanket States which as I and the active
States where the blanket States
comprises sensory in the active States
notice what I've also done here I've
swapped out the log probability here for
a free energy functional that is a
function of the blanket States and this
object here which will become quite
crucial later on which is a a
probability distribution over the
internal states that is parameterized by
the expected internal States a bit
subtle though but that's going to come
very important later on but the two key
things that emerge from this relatively
straightforward analysis first of all
the internal and active states which
we'll call autonomous States share the
same function so it'll look as if my
internal brain and the way I act and try
to do the same thing so we come back
this notion that they're both trying to
minimize say prediction error or in this
instance more generally minimizing by
this gradient flow this variational free
energy functional clearly because of the
structure of the Markov blanket
this variation free energy does not
depend upon the external States so
notice that this thing here is not a
function of the external state is a
function of a function of the external
states that parameterize by the internal
states
so I'll just preempt or foreshadow some
of the due respect geometry conclusion
so what we have here is a gradient flow
that can be written down as a functional
not of external States but as a function
of a
stern states but as a functional of
beliefs about probabilistic beliefs
about external states that is never in
and of itself directly influenced by the
external states but just what the
internal space in that think about or
parameterize what the internal States
parameterize in terms of a belief
distribution over the external states so
that's a bit heavy so let me make it a
little bit lighter so this free energy
functional could have many
interpretations and clearly on the
present analysis undergirds all of the
self-organization that we've been
talking about I'm just making the point
here I can now try to go through this
quickly the point I'm it is being made
here is that this basic structure this
basic mechanics were internal states of
a system and their action upon their
world can be construed or it looks as if
they are minimizing this free energy
functional here of the blanket date in
their sensory data and what they
currently encode it looks very much like
for example action and beliefs trying to
minimize free energy or maximize the
negative of that basically value where
value is simply the probability of a low
probability of your blanket States being
in a particular configuration so this if
you like can be viewed as a sort of a
mathematical backdrop to reinforcement
learning optimal control theory in
economists expected utility theory if on
the other hand you had been brought up
in terms of information theory then this
value function the law of probability
the kinds of blanket states I unlikely
to be found in the ones I prefer to be
found in that define me understand the
negative of that logarithm that's known
as self information and information
theory
treiber's call it surprisal we'll just
call it surprised this free energy
quantity is another bound on that
surprise here and if we think of this
optimized aid from the point of view of
optimization what we are saying is that
we're trying to minimize our surprise
and in so doing we can unpack that in
terms of things like integration
information theory minimum redundancy
principle of Horace Barlow and indeed
the free energy principle that we're
going to casually mention throughout
this presentation that's nice because
the expected value if I do this on
average over time the expected value of
self information or surprises entropy
which means it looks as if this
minimization take on this gradient flow
will be in the service of resisting the
dissipation and decay and disorder
entailed by having a high entropy and
it'll look as if it's consistent with
the principles of self-organization
or synergetics if you're in laser
physics or if you're physiologist they
look by homeostasis just keeping things
within bounds minimizing homeostatic
surprises if you're a statistician you
would look at this conscious AR this is
a probability of some blanket States or
data that I have access to from the app
that are a product of the outside world
under some model here so hitherto this
has been a Markov blanket but now I'm
gonna say no way this is actually we
know from a statistical point of view
it's going to stand in for a model and
this is known as Bayesian model evidence
also known as the marginal likelihood
because I've marginalized out all the
external causes of my blanket States
here so then we can sort of speak to
people in the like the brazing Bayesian
brain hypothesis people who look at the
brain as accumulating evidence and get
back to predictive processing and it's
special cousins or variants such as
predictive coding oh yeah so the Markov
blanket this was sent to me by one of my
young colleagues who moved over to
America he's just had a little baby
and his wife bought him a Markov blanket
so if you want to Markov blanket you can
get these in America so here's a little
Kyra making our inferences first
inferences about the world through
through her own mark that's Markov on
the blanket itself right so information
geometry I'm gonna use numerical
simulations here just to show how these
things arise and how you can think about
what we've talked about in terms of that
a Bayesian mechanics
in terms of something called generalized
synchrony so but let me just take you
through this with it with an
illustration what we've done here is
just create a little universe a
primordial soup by writing down
equations of motion for 128 little
particles or macromolecules each of
which has their autonomous dynamics in
fact based upon a Lorentz attractor and
we've equipped these this ensemble of
synthetic molecules with strong and weak
attractions and repulsions the details
are irrelevant you can generally get
this kind of behavior from any set of
differential equations the reason we
wrote these down is that now we know
exactly the influences that one particle
exerts over another particle and because
we know that we can actually go in and
identify a Markov blanket and then ask
the question is there a little Markov
blanket or a little thing or a particle
inside this soup and if so does it look
as if it's conforming to the Bayesian
brain or conforming to houris borrows
principle of minimum redundancy so I'm
showing the same data here but where
I've color-coded all of those molecules
once they have attained non-equilibrium
steady state as to whether there are
external states that are hidden beyond
the Markov blanket so therefore
sometimes referred to as hidden States
sensory states that as is typical in
these simulations are under written or
above the active states in red then
cells
enshroud the internal states what we see
here is something that's not unlike a
little cryin or viral particles their
particle just wriggling around in its
primordial soup having attained this
non-equilibrium steady state and
coursing in terms of its state space
over this attracting set so this allows
us to ask a question do the internal
states the blue states appear to infer
the causes of their sensory states the
magenta states in other words are they
do they look as if they're doing a
gradient flow on this model evidence as
Bayesian model evidence sometimes
referred to by people like a top who are
self evidencing and indeed they do it's
illustrated in this graphic here so what
we've done here is find a mixture of
internal states that predicts a mixture
of the motion of the external states so
this will be a little bit like finding a
neuronal population or a mixture of
neuro neurons in a small brain that
responded to say motion in the outside
world communicated by via the sensory
state so the visual epithelium and when
we look for this we try to identify
those mixtures that maximally show a
correlation we do indeed find that the
internal states are in some way
parameterizing or encoding or
representing the behavior of the
external states despite the fact they
can't see them directly so what we've
done here is just plot the prediction of
the external state as a function of the
internal state the expected internal
state over time along with ninety
percent confidence intervals and the
actual external motion in cyan here
and you can see that there's a pretty
good inference going on and
interestingly remember before I was
talking about the expected internal
states that capital mu that actually is
important because of what it allows me
to do is to sort of look at the expected
internal states and expected external
states and just see this sync as
synchronization manifold that on average
when the internal states are like this
the external states are roughly like
this if I go through and is pick out
excursions here and overlay themselves
on each other to get at these averages
here what we see is something very much
like what we see in electromagnetic as
that is of the human brain and cognitive
neuroscience for example which is a
simulated event-related potentials
there's a one from the empirical
literature and this is that is
overlaying these fluctuations of
internal states that are themselves
predictive of external states so I've
used the term synchronization manifold
here deliberately because we're all
we're looking at here is something that
has been known for centuries in fact
introduced the notion wasn't used by
history no Christian equivalents as
synchronization of chaos and generalized
synchronization so for those of you who
haven't come across this before it's
most famously articulated by the
observation that when you have many
clocks suspended from the same wall or
the same beam in terms of engineering we
call them loosely coupled dynamical
systems they will never tably come to
swing in unison and in synchrony so that
is the only attracting set that they can
possibly occupy and that exactly
describes this generalized synchrony
between the outside and the inside that
we're witnessing here so from our point
of view this is actually a drawing by
Huygens himself of two clocks suspended
from the same beam one clock we think
all the internal states
the outside world can be the other clock
and the beam become the blanket states
with the active and sensory components
here
I like this perspective because it
highlights the pure symmetry of this
structure so if you subscribe to the
notion that you're trying to infer your
universe then you also are committed to
the idea that your universe is actually
trying to infer you which actually is an
interesting perspective when it comes to
things like eco niche construction like
anyway just looking at the that
synchronization manifold a little bit
more closely it has within it a
structure which holds the key to this
dual aspect information geometry that I
have repeatedly mentioned and it's a
very simple consequence if I simply plot
a little state space with internal
states here in external states there and
I do so for every given blanket state
say sensory input then it has to be the
case there must be a probability
distribution for any given blanket State
over the internal states and the
external states now it's self-evident
it's obvious but it has a fundamental
implication what it means is that for
every blanket state there is an expected
internal state that effectively via this
synchronization manifold Karamat rises a
belief distribution over the external
states so just by having a Markov
blanket I'm conditioning the inside and
the outside
on any given blanket state it must be
the case that on average the internal
states in some sense represent the
external states and we can formalize
that in terms of information geometry I
just put this slide up if you want to
talk about what is information geometry
we can do that this slides like this
panel is just meant to intimate that
there are there are two kinds of
information geometry is going on here
there's a kind of information geometry
that you would be dealing with if you
were a physicist
dealing with the statistical
thermodynamics of this little soup it's
a probability distributions over the
internal states in and of themselves and
from that you can spin off dissipation
fluctuation dissipation integral
fluctuation theorems the second law of
thermodynamics should you want to and
there's another kind of information
geometry going on here because for every
expected internal state there's another
probability distribution over external
States about external States that has
its own information geometry which means
as I move around in my internal state
space I am moving in two spaces at the
same time one is the space of the Laika
configurations on average that I will
occupy on the inside but at the same
time I'm moving around in an information
geometry which is about things on the
outside the causes of my grandkids
States or my sensorial so in summary
internal space parameterize
probabilistic beliefs about external
States and equip them with a dual aspect
geometry so let me just summarize we've
done all the heavy lifting now in this
talk and so let's summarize where we
come from as you know under this
physicists take on self-organization of
things that are equipped with Markov
blanket the existence of a Markov
blanket necessarily implies a partition
of states into internal states and their
blanket States no miss sensor United
States and external states that are
hidden behind the blanket and because
active States change but are not changed
by external states they will appear to
minimize the entropy of external states
and their Markov blanket and this means
that action will appear to minimize the
structural and functional integrity of
the Markov blanket and this has been
framed very elegantly by people like
varela and his colleagues in terms of
auto piecess internal states appear to
infer the hidden causes of sensory
states by maximizing
amazing model evidence and influence
those causes through action and we would
put a bathing gloss on that in terms of
an inactive kind of inference and in
virtue of the implicit generalized
synchrony there must be there if there's
a Markov blanket there must be there if
something exists there exists a dual
aspect information geometry in which
expected internal states parameterised
conditional beliefs / external states
again conditioned upon the Markov
blanket so let me just close now by
taking the considerations to the next
level predicated on this
representational or dual aspect geometry
and see what they might mean for
sentience but to do that I've got to if
you like provide a taxonomy of different
kinds of self evidencing that you get
from this framework so here's a Markov
blanket again just to remind you we've
got our Markov blanket partition here
with the mark of blankets and we can
lump the the internal states and the
active states as these sort of free
energy minimizing prediction error
minimizing states that lend a system a
degree of autonomy and call them
autonomous states under by alpha in a
minute the blanket states comprise the
sensor net if states and then together
these can be thought of as the particle
in question either a brain or a the
sinners don't look at the equations what
I want to do here is just show you where
two different ways of unpacking this
phasing mechanics come from depending
upon how far you want to go in terms of
the mathematical formalism so largely
what we've done so far is start off with
the assumption that there is a universe
that has Noren dynamics with random
fluctuations and flows and we've
quantified or
enumerated the amplitude of these random
fluctuations in terms of this gamma here
this inverse precision and if this is
true at non equivalent steady state when
things have characteristics from
measured over time then the solution
requires this relationship to be true
the flow is related to the gradients of
surprise if the thing in addition has a
Markov blanket I'm stupid to believe so
it must have then this applies to this
and we had now have this hand-in-hand
internal perception like dynamic an
active dynamic both in the surface of
minimizing or minimizing surprisal that
we can write in terms of this
variational function that depends upon
this parameterised belief about the
external states mathematically that's a
a variational density or approximate
posterior density parameterize by the
internal states and we can write down
things like the free energy principle as
a principle a variational principle of
least action where the action is
in this instance denoted by the active
States but action also has an another
meaning
action in physics means the time or the
path integral of energy so there's a
whole other layer to this kind of
argument and which I'm going to show you
in a second but let me just see how far
we can get with this kind of formalism
so if I commit to that those dynamics
and just write down some of these
probability distributions and just
integrate those equations of motion then
you can get quite a long way in terms of
simulating active sentence or active
inference so what we've done here is is
just write down a generative model in
terms of that probability over external
states and the blanket the consequences
the blanket States and so then we can
derive a free energy functional write
down the equations of motion
in this instance just for your interest
this little agent has the belief that
there is an invisible object point
that's pulling its finger around a
trajectory that is itself prescribed by
a neurons attractor and by suitably
configuring some nonlinear mappings when
it acts to fulfill those beliefs to
minimize his prediction errors in this
instance the predictions about what he
should see and feel that it's actually
doing so it's causing its sensations by
moving its hand around we can get it to
simulate things like writing and because
we are generating that writing on that
action we can think of this in terms of
action but also action observations so
by replaying this in the absence of any
proprietary predictions we can start to
simulate action observation and mirror
neuron like behaviors in silico I won't
go into any details there or I'm wanted
to do with this slide is say that just
with these very fast gradient flows of a
predictive processing predicted coding
like flavor you can get quite a long way
in terms of simulating autonomous
behavior both in terms of inferring and
acting and indeed inferring what you see
being enacted but there's a different
kind of autonomous behavior that may be
important for understanding the way that
we actually operate as opposed to say an
insect or a virus or a thermistor might
might operate and that's in terms of
action as a pathogen go into the future
so the whole other bunch of physics you
can bring to the table here again
leveraging the contributions of richard
fineman in terms of the path integral
formulation of quantum electrodynamics
we can tell this same story but not in
terms directly of the fokker-planck
equation but it's equivalent
in terms of a path integral formulation
where now we're talking not about
variational free energies but
variational actions that are integrals
of this free energy functional or it's
its basis which is the surprisal over
time and this can be decomposed into all
sorts of interesting components that
kinetic energy have an independent path
dependent terms that's from our point of
view not so interesting it's the
homologue the ensues when we adopt the
Markov blanket and what comes out of
that now is a slightly different
perspective on the way that we can look
as if we are minimizing the path
integral of variational free energy and
this leads us to the notion of planning
as inference it leads us to choosing
actions now that we think will in the
future have a trajectory or path through
state space that is the least surprising
on average or conforms to our prior
beliefs about the sorts of states that I
will encounter in the future so now but
simply we have a statistical physics
explanation or calculus for planning and
this is the last one last slides no this
is just an illustration when you put
that kind of mechanics in silico and
simulate action now not simply doing the
gradient descent on variational free
energy but actually choosing paths of
action into the future planning to
minimize on average they expected
variation for energy in the future you
can start to simulate things like
saccadic searches hunting for
information it's going to reduce the
expected surprise uncertainty by looking
over there as opposed to looking over
there in brief this simulation is a
showing the the the evidence
accumulation through an epistemic
foraging of the visual field that is
mediated
by little saccadic eye movements
gathering information to resolve
uncertainty about these conditional
beliefs about the causes the external
states of the sensory input here
disambiguating between upright sideways
and an inverted face so this slide
summarizes the if you like the end point
of this most elaborated form of free
energy minimization what it says is you
can think of this as so senses sensory
information coming in you evaluate your
or you change your internal states to
optimize your beliefs about external
states through this variational or
approximate posterior conditional belief
distribution here simply by minimizing
free energy that can be broken down into
in accuracy in complexity and then you
use that to work out what would happen
in the future if I did this all that and
that entails a minimization or that
selection entails a minimization of the
expected free energy and interesting the
expected inaccuracy becomes ambiguity
the expected complexity becomes risk so
now what we have is a calculus from
first principles that gives you a
description of agents that are risk
minimizing and information seeking in
the sense that they want to minimize
their ambiguity and indulge in that kind
of visual palpation that does this
epistemic foraging or responding to
epistemic affordances and we saw in the
previous slide so in summary well this
is not a summary this is levels of
conversation that we can now have
hopefully if we have time about how far
you can take this and what different
levels of garrotted models would be
required to support different kinds of
active engagement with your world via
sensations that could be assets or ium
could have sentience and what does what
was the difference between an
unconscious inference in the sense of
hellhole
and literary thinking and planning about
the future does that require deep
genitive models and the consequences of
action what does that mean for autonomy
and agency how do things become how do
we lose the normal transparency we
haven't talked about a precision but
that may be an important aspect this
encoding uncertainty in these belief
distributions of external states and
what does it mean to have the hypothesis
the fantasy that I am myself and does
this underwrite subjective consciousness
and self-awareness so these are
questions that I don't have answers to
but I thought might be the kinds of
questions that at least some people in
the audience might want to might want to
speak to and so I'll give the last word
to helmoltz again objects always
imagined as being present in the field
of vision as would have to be there in
order to produce the same impression on
the nervous mechanism so with that I
just wanted to thank those people whose
ideas that I've been talking about and
of course thank you for your attention
thank you very much indeed
you